https://blog.mozilla.org/netpolicy/2020/09/12/indias-ambitious-non-personal-data-report-should-put-privacy-first-mozilla/

Search
After almost a year’s worth of deliberation, the Kris Gopalakrishnan Committee released its draft report on non-personal data regulation in India in July 2020. The report is one of the first comprehensive articulations of how non-personal data should be regulated by any country and breaks new ground in interesting ways. While seemingly well intentioned, many of the report’s recommendations leave much to be desired in both clarity and feasibility of implementation. In Mozilla’s response to the public consultation, we have argued for a consultative and rights respecting approach to non-personal data regulation that benefits communities, individuals and businesses alike while upholding their privacy and autonomy.
We welcome the consultation, and believe the concept of non-personal data will benefit from a robust public discussion. Such a process is essential to creating a rights-respecting law compatible with the Indian Constitution and its fundamental rights of equality, liberty and privacy.
The key issues outlined in our submission are:
Mitigating risks to privacy: Non-personal data can also often constitute protected trade secrets, and its sharing with third parties can raise significant privacy concerns. As we’ve stated before, information about sales location data from e-commerce platforms, for example, can be used to draw dangerous inferences and patterns regarding caste, religion, and sexuality.
Clarifying community data: Likewise, the paper proposes the nebulous concept of community data while failing to adequately provide for community rights. Replacing the fundamental right to privacy with a notion of ownership akin to property, vested in the individual but easily divested by state and non-state actors, leaves individual autonomy in a precarious position.
Privacy is not a zero-sum construct: More broadly, the paper focuses on how to extract data for the national interest, while continuing to ignore the urgent need to protect Indians’ privacy. Instead of contemplating how to force the transfer of non-personal data for the benefit of local companies, the Indian Government should leverage India’s place in the global economy by setting forth an interoperable and rights respecting vision of data governance.
Passing a comprehensive data protection law: The Indian government should prioritize the passage of a strong data protection law, accompanied by reform of government surveillance. Only after the implementation of such a law that makes the fundamental right of privacy a reality for all Indians to all should we begin to look into non-personal data.
The goal of data-driven innovation oriented towards societal benefit is a valuable one. However, any community-oriented data models must be predicated on a legal framework that secures the individual’s rights to their data, as affirmed by the Indian Constitution.  As we’ve argued extensively to MeitY and the Justice Srikrishna Committee, such a law has the opportunity to build on the globally standard of data protection set by Europe, and position India as a leader in internet regulation.
We look forward to engaging with the Indian government as it deliberates how to regulate non-personal data over the coming years.
Our full submission can be found here.
Previous article
Mozilla offers a vision for how the EU Digital Services Act can build a better internet
September 8, 2020
Next article
Mozilla applauds TRAI for maintaining the status quo on OTT regulation, upholding a key aspect of net neutrality in India
September 14, 2020
More articles in “Data Governance”
Mozilla releases recommendations on EU Data Strategy
June 5, 2020
Bringing California’s privacy law to all Firefox users in 2020
December 31, 2019
Trusted Recursive Resolvers – Protecting Your Privacy with Policy and Technology
December 9, 2019
Mozilla files comments on NTIA’s proposed American privacy framework
November 20, 2018
Mozilla Statement on Recent Reports of Aadhaar Data Being Breached (again)
May 1, 2018
Recent articles
Mozilla teams up with Twitter, Automattic, and Vimeo to provide recommendations on EU content responsibility
December 9, 2020
Mozilla reacts to publication of the EU Democracy Action Plan
December 3, 2020
Four key takeaways to CPRA, California’s latest privacy law
November 20, 2020
Mozilla DNS over HTTPS (DoH) and Trusted Recursive Resolver
(TRR) Comment Period:
Help us enhance security and privacy online
November 18, 2020
Mozilla Mornings on addressing online harms through advertising transparency
October 19, 2020
Love the Web?
Get the Mozilla newsletter and help us keep it open and free.
I’m okay with Mozilla handling my info as explained in this Privacy Policy.
Sign up now
We will only send you Mozilla-related information.
Thanks!
If you haven’t previously confirmed a subscription to a Mozilla-related newsletter you may have to do so.
Please check your inbox or your spam filter for an e-mail from us.
(TRR) Comment Period:
Help us enhance security and privacy online
November 18, 2020
India’s ambitious non personal data report should put privacy first, for both individuals and communities
September 12, 2020
Practicing Lean Data and Defending “Lean Data”
August 20, 2020
Australian watchdog recommends major changes to exceptional access law TOLA
July 27, 2020
The Facts: Mozilla’s DNS over HTTPs (DoH)
February 25, 2020
Uncategorized
Mozilla reacts to publication of the EU Democracy Action Plan
December 3, 2020
Four key takeaways to CPRA, California’s latest privacy law
November 20, 2020
Mozilla Partners with the African Telecommunications Union to Promote Rural Connectivity
October 1, 2020
By embracing blockchain, a California bill takes the wrong step forward.
August 6, 2020
The Open Technology Fund’s vital role for democracy worldwide should not be undermined
July 27, 2020
Trust
Mozilla reacts to publication of the EU Democracy Action Plan
December 3, 2020
Mozilla DNS over HTTPS (DoH) and Trusted Recursive Resolver
(TRR) Comment Period:
Help us enhance security and privacy online
November 18, 2020
Mozilla Mornings on addressing online harms through advertising transparency
October 19, 2020
Mozilla files comments with the European Commission on safeguarding democracy in the digital age
September 17, 2020
Australian watchdog recommends major changes to exceptional access law TOLA
July 27, 2020
Europe
Mozilla Mornings on addressing online harms through advertising transparency
October 19, 2020
The EU’s Current Approach to QWACs (Qualified Website Authentication Certificates) will Undermine Security on the Open Web
October 8, 2020
Mozilla files comments with the European Commission on safeguarding democracy in the digital age
September 17, 2020
Mozilla offers a vision for how the EU Digital Services Act can build a better internet
September 8, 2020
Mozilla’s response to EU Commission Public Consultation on AI
June 22, 2020
Security
Mozilla DNS over HTTPS (DoH) and Trusted Recursive Resolver
(TRR) Comment Period:
Help us enhance security and privacy online
November 18, 2020
The EU’s Current Approach to QWACs (Qualified Website Authentication Certificates) will Undermine Security on the Open Web
October 8, 2020
Australian watchdog recommends major changes to exceptional access law TOLA
July 27, 2020
Análise da Mozilla: a proposta de lei sobre notícias falsas do Brasil prejudica a privacidade, a segurança e a liberdade de expressão
June 29, 2020
Mozilla’s analysis: Brazil’s fake news law harms privacy, security, and free expression
June 29, 2020
Data protection
India’s ambitious non personal data report should put privacy first, for both individuals and communities
September 12, 2020
Bringing California’s privacy law to all Firefox users in 2020
December 31, 2019
India’s new data protection bill: Strong on companies, step backward on government surveillance
December 10, 2019
Trusted Recursive Resolvers – Protecting Your Privacy with Policy and Technology
December 9, 2019
Indian government allows expanded private sector use of Aadhaar through ordinance (but still no movement on data protection law)
March 5, 2019
User Rights
Criminal proceedings against Malaysiakini will harm free expression in Malaysia
July 8, 2020
Bringing California’s privacy law to all Firefox users in 2020
December 31, 2019
Trusted Recursive Resolvers – Protecting Your Privacy with Policy and Technology
December 9, 2019
Mozilla Mornings on the future of EU content regulation
August 22, 2019
Building on the UK white paper: How to better protect internet openness and individuals’ rights in the fight against online harms
Mozilla’s new Do Not Track dashboard: Firefox users continue to seek out and enable DNT
May 3, 2013
Firefox getting smarter about third-party cookies
February 25, 2013
